[Music] so um so we'll continue looking at
uh the reinforcement the full reinforcement
learning problem so we left off uh where we
defined U markco addition process right and
um so today's class will probably be a short one
okay uh because the next thing next topic I need
to start requires me to define a lot of notations
and stuff like that so if I start that today I'll
probably end up just defining the notation
today and then when I start again next week
I'll ask you I'll will have to ask you to recall
the notation and stuff like that or spend time
writing it out again so I'll not do it so if I
finish uh whatever I want to uh before the proof
start right I'll just stop today so I'll not start
the notations okay so let's see how it goes uh
so right so we we started looking at
markup addition process last time so
we said that it is specified by set
of States actions right transition
probabilities
and right and possibly a gamma so if you look
at the uh the RL textbook right uh they leave
out the GMA right if you look at any o textbook
where also mdps are used widely right uh they
would have the GMA in there right so for
them GMA is a very inherent part of the
problem uh but in the in the RL books you
would see that they would leave out the
gamma even though I mean GMA is inherent
part of the problem it somehow they just
don't acknowledge the fact that gamma changes
the solution right explicitly in the problem
definition itself so this is essentially
what an mdp is all about so what I'll do
is um uh walk through uh one of the examples
from the textbook right so I'm I'm sticking
to the textbook example so you can go back and
read the book um and also because it's uh kind
of makes the course more related to the the
the the minor guys here okay so let's take
the example of a recycling robot from the book
so how many of you have been reading the book
okay the number went up by two since last time
uh okay good uh so do you remember the recycling
robot yeah so what was the thing about are
three states where it goes and searches for
the C goes and actually searches for the C the
second state is where it waits for some someone
to come and do a c okay on the third status
it goes back to the charger to charge battery
so it has to take an action between these
three states based on the battery level it
has uhuh and based on that they will be
rewards whenever it HS a can a reward of
one will be given whenever it runs out of
battery a reward ofus 3 will be given to
otherwise H okay so it's interesting did they
just turn on the mic or something any interesting
that he used uh uh the description
States okay uh so people heard him
any so I'll repeat it uh since I seem to have
the louder mic so you know that those can also
pick up uh but I seem to have the louder mic so
let me repeat it um so that is this robot okay uh
that has been created for the express purpose of
switch Barat okay so it goes around the building
and finds all the empty cans and gathers it and
uh puts it in some kind of a um you know trash
recovery system right recycling system or whatever
so for every can the bot gathers it's going to get
a reward of one right this is a number I'm pulling
out of the hand right so let's not talk about the
reward now right so the the robot is supposed
to gather cans that's essentially what we wanted
to do but uh being a robot it's going to have a
limited amount of power that it can spend right
it has a limited amount of battery power that it
can spend so it has to choose carefully how it
spins the battery right it can go around looking
for cans right and uh if it's going to run out
of battery uh then it can do one of two things it
can recharge itself right or it can just sit in a
place like a trash can and expect people to drop
the uh empty cans into that bot okay just sits
sits in a place and uh people can just use it like
a trash can right so this is essentially the setup
so I have this bot that should I would like it to
go actively gather cans but I also don't like it
to run out of battery because if it runs out of
battery somebody has to go physically either roll
the robot or carry the lift the robot and take it
to a charging station and charge it okay that's a
very painful operation so I really don't want
it to run out of battery but then I don't want
it to just sit idle as as well because what it's
supposed to do is gather cans right so how would
you uh model this problem so what are the states
and uh what are the actions what should be the
reward reward seems to be easy right so well
what you wanted to do he wanted to gather cans
so whenever it gathers can whenever it gathers
a can you give it a reward right so whenever
it gathers a can you give it a reward of plus
one right so I I'm going to call this R can
+ one right then what you don't want it to
do you don't want it to run out of battery
so large H it's yeah something large right
so yeah so I would I would have preferred to
give it minus 10 or something but since
I'm walking through the example in the
book okay so it's a minus 3 right uh so it's not
that bad I mean if you can collect 15 cans and
then die is okay right so it's it's not to
it's not it's not that that better thing so
what else uh if it charges huh if it charges if
it chooses to charge right so what what happens
do we give what do we do for it you think you
should give it a positive reward or [Music]
why does no reward make sense recharge he'll
give recharge yeah just just the heck for heck of
getting that reward it'll get recharged right but
then recharging is also good we want to convey the
fact that recharging also good so it's better than
running out of battery and if you recharge you
have the potential for getting more rewards in the
future because you go out and seek more cans right
so that way you have an indirect uh incentive for
recharging because in the future it allows you to
do something better right if you just look at the
immediate reward it looks like a bad thing but if
you think about it so in the future you're making
it more attractive for recharge I mean you look
at the future outcomes recharging is also pretty
attractive okay can we scale it as an if it is
very low if it is below a threshold or something
what is below threshold POS if the charge no no
this is not this is if you think about it this is
more to do with actions or something yeah kind of
outcom on the battery levels Aces recharging uh
you could you could make it all the more detailed
you can make it as detailed as you want right
now now comes the Crux how detailed do you want
to make the representation to be do you want to
make it a real number saying okay how much battery
charge I have get a continuous State you could get
a continuous State then right so what do you want
to do you want to do some kind of discretization
right so if I want to do discretization so how do
I discretize ah that brings us to another question
completely we forgot to answer that question what
is the state battery charge the battery charge
level should be the state right and then anything
[Music] else the number of cans it has
aity no let's just assume that magically
it takes a can and transports it to
yeah but that's an interesting thing if it has
a finite carrying capacity then you probably
need to throw in uh how many cans it has
so before it has to make a trip to theum
dump Dumping Ground or something like that
so let's assume for the time being it's uh
so as soon as you put a can into that that is a
teleporter that takes it to The Dumping Ground
okay or the bot has an infinite carry I'm just
trying to make the problem simpler right if
you want to make the problem more and more
realistic right you'll have to think about
a whole bunch of other things right for example
I'm kind of making it at a very very high level
I'm not talking about the pose and I mean the
pose of the robot right the velocity which the
bot is moving so all of these things you need
right if you want to actually going to control
the bot right then just assuming all of those are
somehow going to be magically taken care of right
so we just assuming that you are only worried
about the uh the charge of the bot right yeah
you a question the action has to be discret yeah
States also discret huh States also discret uh no
we have been talking about only discrete States
and discrete actions so far we have not talked
about continuous States and continuous actions
but you have continuous State continuous AC
mdps okay so the state is going to be
the charge right and possibly number of
cans right and other things uh but for the
time being I'm just going to say I'm not
going to care about all of that we'll just look
at chart just to keep it a simple simple example
right uh and also keeping it in sync with
the book so and again so what do I do with
charge I can treat it as a number in which
case I'll have to figure out how to handle
a continuous value right or I can start
discretizing it so how will I discretize
it yeah so I can well percentage is also not a
discretization unless you round it off okay so
uh yeah so you could do something like that or
it could be even more aggressive right I could
do low medium high right and if you really
stop and think about it when would you if if
I say if I do low medium high or something like
that when would I I actually change my decision
about charging versus not charging right only
when I low right so in some sense you could
even try operating with high and low right or
sufficient and low or whatever right since we
don't know the distance from the charging point
is it mid is also probably mid is also problem
yeah great so I don't I'm not having my location
at all here right so assuming that there's always
a convenient charging Point located nearby okay
so it's not like there single base station I have
to go there so as soon as I find out okay I'm
running out of CH let's assume that as long as
the battery is low I can still get to a charging
port in fact I'm going to assume even something
stronger so I could with some probability keep
operating even if my battery is low right uh
and I still not run out of so okay assumption
I make is the following whenever I say recharge
okay I'll have enough battery power to reach
the nearest Recharge station and recharge so
after I pick the option recharge I will not run
out of battery power this again very simplifying
assumption right this makes it easier for us to
draw pictures as I will do in a minute right but
all the points that are being raised are very
good points right so when you start trying to
model a real system right these are all calls that
you have to make right so what is it that I would
throw into my state right what ises say that
I can ignore right and so on so forth and
uh yeah so um so pal do you remember
the homework assignment we are asking
them yeah the third one we are asking
them we're giving them a word problem
and asking them to construct an
mdp out of it right you think
so huh new ass new assignment third
assignment yeah yeah the one that was
released today today today today morning
yeah it was released yesterday then your
time traveling okay yeah it do release this
morning uh yeah so the new assignment and it's
due on uh Fe 14th yeah do on 14th huh 14th
which is what 9 Sunday huh Sunday yeah mhm
well plan ahead if it's
important to you finish on the
13th or as it's more likely for a lot of
people if you have nothing to do on 14th have a
whole last huh last question is last
question is that right so there's a
word problem and expect you to construct
so you can think of similar things but
that is a more constrained word problem so
you'll you'll see that there's not too many
ways in which you can construct an mdp
out of it so but then the idea is that
a lot of design choices that you make when they
give you a problem specification there are a lot
of choices that you make when you go from the
problem specification to an mdp right so when
you're talking about uh designing a reinforcement
learning solution for a problem the things that
you have to decide are the states the actions and
the rewards these are the three things that you
have to decide and when you're are constructing
an mdp additionally you'll have to figure out
what this the transition probabilities are also
going to be because without that you can't solve
the problem right but in uh we are trying to use
reinforcement learning techniques to solve these
problems as we'll see later on you don't need
the transition Dynamics right you don't need
to explicitly model the transition Dynamics but
you still need to make choices for States actions
and rewards so that's where we are right
now so after we finish this I'll tell you
some simple way of Consulting the transition
probability for the robot but that's fine so
essentially what I'm going to do charge is going
to be now low or high okay and then what about
actions there's no pick up let's say when I
actively find a can I automatically pick it
up okay so I'll go so explore essentially or uh as
they see in as they say in the book actively seek
cans because explore is overloaded right so
we have explore exploit those kinds of things
already so I don't want to have an action called
explore okay uh so you have actively seek can
or wait for can or recharge
right so is there anything else that we need to
Define here zero Char St H zero charge State um
well yeah so I I'll tell you how you can
get around that yeah that's a good point
so maybe you need a zero charge state but
I'll also tell you how to get around that
right so the Assumption we are going to make
is if you run out of charge somebody is going
to take you and charge you right then you're
going to get this penalty of minus 3 so what
does that mean so from low I can actually go
to high with a penalty of minus 3 okay so that
is that is equivalent to the zero charge state
so how long it be in the charge St how you know
that you can make it more complex so
right now I'm assuming once you plug
it into charge I don't worry
about it until fully charged
later right see this is another thing which you
was an interesting point because I've have
discretized it into low and high right so when
will it run out of charge when it when it will
go from high to low state so if it high is 100%
high right it's probably not going to go to the
low State when it take an action but if high is
say 40% High almost surely as soon as it Tak an
action it is going to go into a low State let's
say 40 is the cut off point right so above 40 I
say high below 40 I say low that's percentages
right 40% I'll say high below 40% I'll say low
almost shly as soon as I take an action it's
going to go to low but then I'm not making this
distinction I made a discretization here right
so what will it look like to me and if I run the
robot multiple times what will it look like to
me sometimes it goes from high to low
sometimes it Go doesn't go from high
to low it stays in high so what is going to
happen here is I'm going to translate this
into the probabilities of transition right so
what is the probability of going from high to l
right in fact uh if I you know if I knew all about
my uh the battery Dynamics if I know about how
much power each and every action takes and if I
modeling this as a continuous valued State there
might not be any spasticity here right I might
be able to tell you very exactly okay now at this
point if this is the action you're doing this is
so much power that you will consume and therefore
the battery will go from high to low so I might
be able to give that to you exactly so in L this
might not be a stochastic system okay I'm only
saying might not be because people have worked
with robots so you know that you might you might
specify as many initial conditions as you want
right the bot will do what it wants to do right
so so it's still be a stochastic system uh but it
could potentially not be a stochastic system if
you know everything about the world right but we
are making it stochastic by virtue of ignoring
certain things that we could potentially know
about the system right and ignoring this makes the
system design a lot simpler maybe we are giving up
some things in terms of how optimal our Solutions
can be but that's a trade-off that you'll often
have to make right so just the formulation itself
is not an easy task you have to think about it
a lot to figure out what will be the right place
to draw the line okay uh so these are the actions
that we have to take so you can actively see
cans Wait For Cans recharge is there something
else that we have to specify so we have specified
the stat we specified the actions we specified
rewards for events right so if I collect a can
I get a plus one right if I run out of battery
I get a minus 3 then if I recharge I get a zero
these are events that could happen in the world
right so these are so I have to relate this to the
states and actions only then I can tell you what
is the expected reward decision we will not talk
about time at all right I told you for that at
least for the initial part of the course we'll not
talk about over time with how long it runs right
so what is it that we need suppose I'm actively
seeking cans what is the probability I'll get a
reward of plus one if I'm actively seeking cans
right what is the probability that I'll find a
can correct right so I need to still specify
that if I'm actively or if I'm waiting for
cans to come right what is the probability that
I'll get a can you think it's a of the first one
because what is the derivative of what of the
first one because if you're waiting fors then
there are no available yeah which means you
no more actively seek right what that which
means you no more actively seek again why
because you're actively seeking again yeah
you decide that are maybe maybe not I don't
I don't know why you chose to move from one
to the other right I mean I could have just
stopped checking because I was running low on
battery so if right so if if if I'm in some
facility where people are just taking cans
and throwing them the dust bin right I might just
happily go sit sit next to the can dispensing uh
place and act as a dpin right I'll be happily
getting rewards right I might not even worry
about recharging or anything right so I might just
choose to stop right so it depends on that depends
on the kind of environment you're operating in
right so even if I act as a Dustbin if if do I
get enough cans then I might not want to seek
right so maybe there is some time of the day
maybe between 12 and 130 or something lot of
cans will come if I just go stand outside the
cafeteria I don't have to actively seek cans maybe
after 130 I have to go around seeking cans right
I don't know depends on the system right I'm not
trying to be too over realistic here uh but I'm
just giving you what are the factors that you have
to take into account right so if you start talking
about what could be optimal policies right then
you're going down a dangerous path that means you
are going to start designing your problem itself
depending on what you think the solution should be
which is a bad thing right you should put in all
the factors about the problem in the design and
then you should go and let the algorithm figure
out what the solution should be so you shouldn't
start thinking about what the solution should be
and then try to create uh create the rewards and
the model itself I'll give you an example of that
after I finish this I'll give you an example of
uh when that became a problem okay uh so is it
clear so now I need to figure out if I actively
seek can okay what is the probability that I
get cans right is there anything else I need to
know trans yeah we'll come to that yeah it's
related to that if I'm actively seeking cans
what is the probability that I'll run out
of battery because that also determines
my reward right right or if I'm waiting
for cans to come what is the probability
I'll run out of battery maybe zero because
I've turned off everything and just waiting
for or maybe there's a leakage that is happening
yeah it's a very small probability that I might
actually run out of battery right so so I
need both of these to actually figure out
what will be the expected reward right for a
state action pair so I need to know what will
be the expected reward so I have to actually
think about both of these things if I am in
a high state right and I'm actively seeking cans
right so what is the probability I'll find a can
does it depend on whether I'm in a high state
or not no right so if I'm actively seeking cans
what is the probability I'll get a can Okay so
that is one thing I need likewise if I'm not
actively seeking cans what is the probability
I'll get a can that is second thing I need on
the other hand if I'm in a high State and actively
seeking cans what is the probability I'll run out
of battery there the state matters right and
likewise if I am in a low State and actively
seeking can what is the probability I'll run out
of battery there are State matters likewise for
waiting for cans if I'm in a high State and
I'm waiting for a can yeah probability of me
running out of battery is very very minuscule
almost zero but if low State and I'm waiting
for a can so even with the leakage power
drawn I might actually run out of battery
so these are the things so you need to know all
of these right for time being I'll say Alpha is
the right the probability of you getting
a can right and bet the probability of you
getting a can if you're waiting and then Alpha
is greater than beta I mean hopefully typically
right we're talking about probabilities
I mean there might be momentarily where
beta is higher than Alpha like I said stand
outside a cafeteria during lunch time but
then overall we going to assume that Alpha is
greater than beta since we have not actually
modeled the the time of day anywhere right we
just going to say Alpha is greater than beta
right so now what else do we
need yet we need to Define
p right so for that what do we need well if
I'm in State high what is the probability
I'll go to state low okay forget about
going to out of battery that's what we
needed for the rewards but for the state
transition so from high to low what is
the probability that will happen if I I am
actively seeking a can so that's basically
what we need right so I'm in State
high I'm actively seeking a can what
is the probability I'll stay in State high
what is the probability I'll go to state
low right so like that uh and likewise if I'm
in state low and I'm actively seeking a can
what is the probability I'll stay in state
low what's the probability I'll go to State
high right and I'm in state low
and I'm waiting for can what is
the probability I'll stay in state low
what is the probability I'll go to State
high right and so on so forth right so these are
all the things that you need for defining the
state transition probabilities okay of course
if I'm in State high and I do action recharge
what do I want we can't right if exactly
so if I'm in state low I do action recharge
with probability one I'll go to State high
right so we'll actually prohibit recharge
action in State high because it doesn't make
sense I'm already fully charged I don't want
to go plugging in again right so we we'll
uh disolve that the only time we change
the current action is when it transitions from
high to low right that's the only time well all
depends right I could just have a stochastic
policy I can say that okay my policy is that
if I in State high with probability point8
I'll search with probability point2 I'll just
stay so I mean so we're not
talking about Solutions here
I'm just talking about defining the
problem this is what I was mentioning
earlier also don't don't get into
how the solution will look like
right sometimes you'll have to think about
how the solution will look like because
you need to know if you're giving the state
sufficient expressiveness so that you know
when the solution should change and things
like that but don't worry too much about
the structure of the solution okay so now we'll
just draw this some kind of a state transition
diagram right so let's do the ACT State high first
so there are two actions from State
high one one is actively seek cans
right so active so what are
the possible outcomes of
active Okay so what is the probability
that I'm going to be in high
Rel I don't know some some values equal is also
possible well depends on how wide my high band is
right and how much power action is going to
consider I don't know just say some numbers
here right what's other action I can take
here right and what is
the something some numbers now is there anything
else I need to specify I need to look at what the
reward is going to be for having done
that right so what will be the reward
here yeah I'll get plus one for a can but
the expected number of cans I'm going to
collect is Alpha right there the probability of me
getting a can so the expected reward will be Alpha
right likewise here the expected what is going to
be okay so from low I again three actions from low
I have three actions not two right
I have three actions so what are the
actions right so I'll do the easy one first
right from low if I do recharge with probability
one I'll go to high and I'll get zero
reward right so now comes the more
interesting one suppose I do weight
here is there any chance that it go to
high I could right so that's also possible
but very low very low probability because
I'm not doing anything so if I already
said 0.1 here is the probability of
discharging so I'll say 0.1 minus
and I still get a can right and this one is
likewise if I'm actively seeking
does it make sense right some small
probability I might not discharge and
they keep acing rewards at Alpha right
but then I might actually discharge with
a high probability and then I go to the
high State and I also get the additional
minus 3 along the way I mean whether you
do this plus beta and plus alpha or not is
again a choice right you can say that hey if I run
out nobody's actually going to give me a can right
so people might snatch away the can I already have
I don't know what so you can choose whatever thing
this is again a choice I just I just chose to
add the alpha and beta here you can choose not
to but you can you get the sense of what we are
doing here right so a very very simple problem
it took us a while to identify all the factors
right and we chose to ignore a whole bunch of
factors because you identified a lot of useful
factors right we chose to ignore a whole bunch
of factors all in order to come up with a simple
tractable mdp right great [Music] [Applause]